Finding Aid for Alpha Phi Omega. Gamma Pi Chapter (University of Michigan) records, 1939-2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Alpha Phi Omega, Gamma Pi Chapter (University of Michigan) records 1939-2010
Alpha Phi Omega. Gamma Pi Chapter (University of Michigan)
9663 Bimu 2
National service fraternity founded on the principles of the Boy Scouts of America and opened to women in 1976. Minute books, officer's reports, correspondence, records of service projects, publications, scrapbooks and photographs.
8 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were donated by the organization (Donor no. 8222 ) in February 1994 and September 2011.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The history of the Gamma Pi chapter of the national service fraternity of Alpha Phi Omega (APO) is one of commitment to the founding principles of fellowship, leadership and service, and reflects the organization's responses to the changing service needs of a large, dynamic university as well as to larger societal mandates for a broadened interpretation of equal opportunity.
On November 2, 1939, a meeting of the Rover Boy Scout group was held at the student union to discuss the formation of a pledge group for a local chapter of Alpha Phi Omega. A year later, members of the pledge group, primarily Rover Scouts, were initiated by APO chapter members from Michigan State University to officially form the Gamma Pi chapter. The national organization had been founded in 1925, in part to provide former boy scouts a college organization based on scouting principles. The bylaws described the purpose of the fraternity as, "to assemble college students in a National Service Fraternity in the fellowship of the principles of the Boy Scouts of America as embodied in its Scout Oath and Law, to develop Leadership, to promote Friendship, and provide Service to humanity."
As a chapter of APO, Gamma Pi had some flexibility in administration of its local programs and activities. Structurally it belonged to Section 54 consisting of the state of Michigan, which was part of a larger Region 6 comprised of Illinois, Indiana, and Michigan, all under the governance of an elected national Board of Directors. Leadership and fellowship opportunities were available at meetings of all three hierarchical levels, and service project ideas and experiences were widely shared.
In October 1970, Gamma Pi chapter proposed language changes in the national bylaws to support membership status for women. Despite an appeal led by the national organization to exclude APO from Title IX ruling, the United States Department of Health Education and Welfare found in 1976 that APO's membership practices were subject to the provisions of Title IX. Full membership opportunities must now be extended to women if university sponsorship were to continue. Women's names appear on the membership roster of Gamma Pi beginning in 1976.
Pledges to APO were invited twice yearly and became full members after demonstrating an understanding of APO history and goals and after performing required service hours.
Gamma Pi's service projects changed from year to year and from decade to decade and included conducting fingerprinting for FBI civilian identification files, soliciting donations for charitable causes, giving campus tours, staffing the student union lounge, ushering at campus events, counting ballots, maintaining an exam file, helping move books at the public library, making recordings for foreign students, and selling student directories. Ongoing projects included providing copy service at cost, distributing and posting campus signs, and sponsoring a yearly blood drive competition with Ohio State University.
The records of the national service fraternity, Alpha Phi Omega (APO), Gamma Pi chapter, document the student organization from its structural roots in 1939 to the present day, and exemplify organizational commitment to the founding principles of leadership, fellowship and service. Since operational policies and procedures are directed by a national Board of Directors, many of the record series contain materials originating from national headquarters. The records are arranged in seven series: Correspondence, Minutes, Service Projects, Scrapbooks and Clippings, Topical, Printed Materials, and Photographs.
Subjects:
Alpha Phi Omega. Gamma Pi Chapter (University of Michigan); Greek letter societies--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Boy Scouts of America.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs.
Genre Terms:
Scrapbooks.
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series contains both incoming and outgoing correspondence from 1940 to 1956, 1960-1970, and 1980-1987, including the chapter's earliest days as a preparatory group, working for official chapter status. Very few records in this series document the years 1971-1980 or after 1987. Records consist of mailings from national headquarters and from other chapters, as well as some internal communication from University of Michigan departments and from local APO members.
  - 1940-1956, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - 1960-1970, 9 folders (Box 1)
  - 1980-1987 (Box 1)
- Minutes
  The Minutes series contains records of weekly membership meetings, executive board meetings and pledge meetings for the years 1939-2003. There are gaps in the minutes, and the more recent minutes tend to be less comprehensive in terms of coverage. Most minutes are grouped by the academic year, generally from September to April, and document planning and progress of varied service projects and social events, in addition to routine chapter business. Also included in this series are a few records of meetings of APO Section 54.
  - November 1939-December 1942 (Box 2)
  - September 1948-February 1958 (Box 2)
  - 1960-1983, 18 folders (Box 2)
  - 1986-1996, 11 folders (Box 2)
  - 1997-1998, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - 2003 (Box 3)
- Service Projects
  The Service Projects series documents both one-time and ongoing projects from the 1960s through the early 1990s, the core of which are the annual Blood Drive challenge competition with Ohio State University and the Campus Sign System service.
  - Blood Drive
    - Chairperson Manual circa 1980-1986 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence and Clippings 1971-1991 (Box 3)
    - Red Cross Procedures circa 1980-1984 (Box 3)
  - Campus Sign System 1966-1970 (Box 3)
  - Service Projects Report undated (Box 3)
  - Service Records
    - 1961-1967 (Box 3)
    - 1970 (Box 3)
    - 1979 (Box 3)
    - 1980 (Box 3)
    - 1981 (Box 3)
    - 1982 (Box 3)
    - 1983-1984 (Box 3)
    - 1985 (Box 3)
    - 1987 (Box 3)
    - 1988-1990 (Box 3)
  - Sturdy Oak Tree 1991 (Box 3)
  - Thank You Letters 1974-2006 (Box 3)
- Topical Files
  The Topical series contains membership rosters prepared by the national headquarters with a running tally of all members initiated, 1940-2002. Pledging procedures are also documented. Especially significant are the annual reports, which document national expectations for the chapter and the chapter's summary of service, fellowship, and leadership activities for each year from 1940-1958. The administrative material includes examples of organizational best practices with compiled officer's notebooks and national leadership materials.
  - Administration
    - Chapter Alcohol Policy undated (Box 4)
    - Chapter Bylaws 2004 (Box 4)
    - Leadership Series 1977, 1980-1982, 1985-1986 (Box 4)
    - National Bylaws and Amendments 1968-1978 (Box 4)
    - Officer Notebooks
      - Awards Chairman circa 1964 (Box 4)
      - Membership Chairman circa 1964 (Box 4)
      - Recording Secretary circa 1964 (Box 4)
      - Second Vice President (Pledgemaster) 1958-1964 (Box 4)
      - Service Chairman circa 1964 (Box 4)
      - Officer Reports, Fall 1984-Winter 1985 (Box 4)
      - Vice President of Service Position Suggestions undated (Box 4)
    - 20th Anniversary 1960 (Box 4)
    - 50th Anniversary 1990 (Box 4)
  - Annual Reports 1940/41-1957/58 (Box 4)
  - Awards 1965-2010 (Box 4)
  - Brochures undated (Box 4)
  - Budgets 1975-1991 (Box 4)
  - Chapter Program Planning Conference 1992 (Box 4)
  - "Forward to the 80s Conference," 1979 (Box 4)
  - Membership
    - Certificates 1956-1982 (Box 4)
    - Rosters 1940-2002 (Box 4)
  - Pledging Procedures
    - General (Box 4)
    - Pledge Program 1989/90 (Box 4)
  - Report on the Status of Women in Alpha Phi Omega 1976-1977, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Resource Survey 1986-1987 (Box 4)
  - Section 54 Material 1971-1992, 4 folders (Box 4)
- Scrapbooks and Photographs
  The Scrapbook and Photographs series records chapter activities, anniversary conferences and convention participation through scrapbooks and photograph albums. An early scrapbook from the 1940s through 1956 includes photographs of the chapter moving to a new office and shows APO members assisting at registration among other activities. Two scrapbooks document, with photographs, service projects from 1960-1963, including Gamma Pi chapter's "Willowpolitan," a holiday season airport bus shuttle service for University students. The bulk of the series documents Gamma Pi activities from 1982 to 2000.
  The photographs include candid photographs of social events such as banquets with the presentation of the Gamma "Pi," and conference social activities. Other photographs document service projects and pledge classes.
  - 1940s-1957 (Box 8)
  - 1960-1961 (Box 4)
  - 1962-1963 (Box 4)
  - 1963-1964 (Box 4)
  - 1968-1969 (Box 4)
  - 1982-1983 (Box 5)
  - 1984-1985, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - 1985-1986 (Box 5)
  - 1986 (Box 5)
  - 1986-1987, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - 1987-1988, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - 1988-1989, 5 folders (Box 6)
  - 1989-1990, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - 1990-1991, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - 1991 (Box 6)
  - 1991 (Box 8)
  - 1991-1992 (Box 7)
  - 1992-1993 (Box 7)
  - 1993-1994 (Box 7)
  - 1994-1995 (Box 7)
  - 1996 (Box 7)
  - 1997 (Box 7)
  - 1999-2000 (Box 7)
  - Photographs, Miscellaneous 1940-1990s (Box 7)
- Audiovisual
  The final series, Audiovisual, contains two VHS tapes documenting the 1991 and 1992 senior shows.
  - Senior Show 1991-1992, 2 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 7)
  - Scrapbook 1940s-1956 (Box 8)
  - Photograph Album 1991 (Box 8)